<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sober conformists answer to a rigid conformists reasons why in this juncture no alteration should be made in the government of the Church of Scotland.</title>
            <author>Ker, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47280</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8036</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12710074</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12710074</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66087</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47280)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66087)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 816:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sober conformists answer to a rigid conformists reasons why in this juncture no alteration should be made in the government of the Church of Scotland.</title>
                  <author>Ker, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Published by a Lover of Peace and Truth,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to William Ker. cf. Wing.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66087:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66087:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SOBER CONFORMISTS ANSWER TO A RIGID CONFORMISTS REASONS.
Why
in this Juncture no Alteration ſhould be made in the GOVERNMENT of the
CHURCH
of SCOTLAND.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 26.4.</bibl>
               <p>Anſwer not a Fool according to his folly, leſt thou alſo be
like unto him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Verſe 5.</bibl>
               <p>Anſwer a Fool according to his folly, leſt he be wiſe in his
own Conceit.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>M. D. Dickſon,</bibl>
               <p>Papiſts hate nothing in Prelacy but what is Presbyterian, and
Presbyterians hate nothing in it but what it Popiſh.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>M. R. Blair,</bibl>
               <p>The Biſhops of England are like the Kings of Judah, ſome good
ſome bad. The Biſhops of Scotland are like the Kings of Iſrael, not a
good one amongſt them all.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed by a Lover of Peace and Truth. Printed in the Year
MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="reasons">
            <pb facs="tcp:66087:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66087:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>REASONS Why in this Juncture no Alteration ſhould be made in
the GOVERNMENT Of the CHURCH of SCOTLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon I.</hi> BEcauſe Epiſcopal Government has not only
the Advantage of Apoſtolick Conſtitution and Natural Reception by all
Chriſtian Churches from CHRIST to <hi>Calvin,</hi> but alſo is found by
Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to be the beſt Adapted for preſervation of Order, Peace and
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea. 2.</hi> Becauſe the moſt of the Gentry and
Burgeſſes have taken the Teſt, and therefore can never without perjury
vote for the Introduction of <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytry,</hi> or chuſe ſuch a
Commiſſioner as may be ſuſpected to favour that way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea: 3.</hi> If <hi>Preſbytry</hi> be voted, then returns
upon you the <hi>Solemn League</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> as is
evident not
only from the preſent proceedings of the <hi>Presbyterian Preachers,</hi>
but
alſo from the Natural Exigence of the thing, it not being poſſible to
conceive a Foundation for parity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, and if the Covenant return then,
beſide the many impieties of that Oath, it muſt make the moſt
conſiderable of the Nation either perjured or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable; And no Man can
have any publick place either in Church or State, but ſuch as ſhall do
pennance for taking the Teſt; and not only ſo, but a great part of the
Laity of the Nation, muſt be reduced to great ſtraits, both in reference to
Conſcience and Intereſt, and the preſent Regular Clergy be turned out,
which will reduce the Church to ſuch Amazing Hardſhips, that the Goſ
pel
ſhall not be preached in three parts of the Kingdom, there not being an
hundred qualified <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea: 4.</hi> Becauſe if <hi>presbytry</hi> ſhall not be
thus eſtabliſhed in its integrity but all that Alteration turn to a
<hi>Non-Epiſcopacy,</hi> and the preſent Presbyters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in their
Offices, then our deplorable Schiſms and Diviſions, will conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue without
a remedy, or elſe the Magiſtrate will take the Government of the Church
upon him, and we muſt have downright <hi>Eraſtianiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea: 5:</hi> Becauſe the eſtabliſhment of
<hi>Presbytry</hi> will have a moſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious influence upon the
<hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> in this Iſland if ever Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſet up its
head. For the Churches of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> muſt
ſtand
on different bottoms, &amp; ſo will be obliged to juſtifie themſelves by
different Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments,<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66087:3"/>which will prove very hard for
<hi>Scotland,</hi> ſeing Presbytry will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid it from <hi>England,</hi>
which opens a door to the re-entry of Popery, which cannot but aleniate the
Affections of the Church of <hi>England</hi> from us, which conſidering
our
own weakneſs will expoſe us a prey to the common Enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea. 6.</hi> To be for Presbytry in this Juncture will
exceedingly diſoblige the Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> whoſe
principles
are known to all <hi>Europe</hi> in this matter, and the Prince alſo who
has
no inclination for the Alteration of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, as he hath
now abundantly declared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea. 7:</hi> Let all thinking Men but reflect upon the Natural
Tempter of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytry, and view it in its Tyrannical, pragmatick, Medling and
Domineering effects which many good Men yet living of all Qualities have
ſeverely felt. Let them likewiſe conſider the Hypocriſie, immorality
and Antichriſtian genius of that party, and then let them vote for it if they
think fit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea: 8:</hi> If the Church of <hi>England</hi> continue as it
is (as undoubtedly is will) and <hi>Scotland</hi> be reduced to
<hi>Presbytry,</hi> then conſidering the bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and reſtleſs
ſpirit of Presbytry, <hi>Scotland</hi> will impoſe, <hi>ſicut ante,</hi>
an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in Doctrine and Diſcipline upon that Nation, which will
commence a new Civil War, the thoughts of which cannot but breed horrour in
all
rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:66087:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF the wounds of a Friend be better than the kiſſes of an
Enemy, they ſhould be far more acceptable then the wounds of an Enemy;
And
therefore I expect ye will not be diſpleaſed with my Freedom in this line
deſigned for preventing your more ſevere and ſhameful Treatment, by
our
<hi>Adverſaries</hi> to whom ye have given great advantage, by ſome
<hi>Reaſons</hi> ye have writen [<hi>why in this Juncture there ſ
hould be
no Alteration of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church of</hi> Scotland] of baffling
our cauſe ſo unſeaſonably and <hi>weakly defended</hi> by you.
For
albeit there are many <hi>ſober Presbyterians</hi> whoſe generous
compaſſion of our preſent ſtaggering condition, would not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
them
to give you ſuch an humbling Repartee, as ye give too large ground for, yet
as we deſerve it not at their hand, who have been ſo cruel to them in
their
low condition; ſo we cannot expect it from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them, eſpecially,
when they are at once encouraged, by the many Diſadvantages of our pre
ſent
circumſtances, and irritated by your extreme bitterneſs againſt them,
and
therefore I adviſe you would recal all the copies of it, which I am hopeful
have not yet ſpread far, for in. genuouſly they are ſo weak, that few of
our perſwaſion will be at the pains to tranſcribe them, and I think they
will be more careful of our Reputation then to ſuffer them to come to the
hands of any <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> as through time they may, if you
prevent it
not. But leſt your vanity make you confidently contemn my counſel; I
ſhall take a little pains to abate your confidence, by ſhewing you how
eaſily and advantagiouſly our Adverſaries with whom I have frequent
converſe can anſwer you.</p>
            <p>But I muſt firſt expreſs my Diſſatisfaction with the
title ye give your paper ſo lyable to the moſt perplexing Exceptions can
be
made againſt us. I doubt not but ye have heard (I have heard it ſo often)
how la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably <hi>Arch-Biſhop P:</hi> was baffled of late by Mr.
<hi>Roger</hi> at <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> upon the like occaſion given
him; Weare
too conſcious to our ſelves, that the ſole ſupport of our intereſt is
but <hi>Civil Laws</hi> (though the <hi>Biſhops</hi> were at the
making them)
and that all <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Authority</hi> is on their ſide; And
therefore ye would be inextricably puzled, if they put the Queſtion to you,
Which of the two is the Government of the <hi>Church of Scotland,</hi> that
which is only introduced by <hi>Civil Laws,</hi> without any
<hi>Eecleſiaſtick Authority,</hi> contrary to the ſtanding Laws of the
Church, never yet repealed by any <hi>Church Judicature,</hi> or that which
is
eſtabliſhed by many National Aſſemblies of the Church, though
contrar
to poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Acts of Parliament, made without any conſequent, far leſ
s
Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Determination of any Church Judicatory.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:66087:4"/>They may likewiſe give you an unanſwerable
challenge of monor polizing the ſpecious name of the <hi>[Church of
Scotland]</hi> to us (excluding them) becauſe we have receded from old
ſtanding <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Laws</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other warrand then
<hi>new Civil Laws</hi> contrary to them; and upon that account charge us
with
<hi>Schiſm</hi> &amp; <hi>unwarrantable ſeparation</hi> from
them, having
no Evaſion left us, but that we are the more numerous part of the Clergy,
which ſcarce makes our Separation tolerable, far leſs juſtifiable.</p>
            <p>But that which is as unbecoming us, as unacceptable to them, is
your pleading <hi>[no Alteration]</hi> which will ſtumble your Readers
with
preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice in the very entry; For how ever difficult it be to prove the
neceſſity of ſuch an intire Alteration as <hi>Presbyterians</hi>
deſire, yet they can eaſily pitch upon many things, which we cannot
ingenuouſly deny ſhould be alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; And the book entituled the
<hi>Reformed Biſhop,</hi> writen by one of our Clergy, opens a wide door
to
them; Yea, we are all of us too ſenſible, that our intereſt has been
ſcrued up to ſo dangerous heights, by the Laws, that there is no ſtable
Baſis left to eſtabliſh it in the Conſciences of thoſe who own it;
And we have Reaſon to fear leſt thoſe odious ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructures of
the
Magiſtrates unbounded <hi>Supremacy</hi> over the <hi>Church,</hi>
ſuch
rigorous impoſitions on the Conſciences of Subjects, and ſo cruel
perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Diſſenters (which by an exceſs of Zeal we have
erected, to be the ſecurities of our cauſe) may ſo much diſcommend
the
whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of our Government, as to endanger the total ruine thereof. And
I
have alwayes thought it a great flaw in the <hi>Epiſcopal Government</hi> in
<hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that as it hath been built upon no other Foundation, and
advanced by no other Methods then <hi>Civil Laws</hi> rigorouſly
executed,
ſo theſe are framed in ſuch an <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and perſecuting
ſtile, that the leaſt turn of Affairs will render them as odious as before
they were grievous to all moderate and judicious Men of both parties.</p>
            <p>And finally, it ſurpaſſeth my imagination, what hath
incouraged you to add <hi>[in this Juncture?]</hi> Its evident that the
whole
preſent Juncture of Affairs hath a bad Aſpect on us, and we can expect
little Favour from ſuch as duely conſider the ſame. What hath
infatuated
you to ſuch an unaccountable confidence? Alace! your Reaſons can never
cancel theſe unhappy Addreſſes to the King, ſo freſh in the
remembrance of all Men; That of the <hi>Primat</hi> ſent to King in name
of
the Clergy, to thank him for the Liberty granted to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi>
ſo full of baſe <hi>ſycophantry,</hi> and <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject flattery,</hi>
that
even the <hi>Popiſh King</hi> was aſhamed of it, which I fear be
printed at
<hi>Fdinburgh</hi> before the Convention, though ye tempt them not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66087:4"/>to the remembrance of it, and that other moſt
unſeaſonable Teſtimony of our Loyalty, expreſsing our Deteſtation
of
the <hi>P. of Orange</hi> his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>England,</hi> as an unjuſ
t and
unnatural Invaſion; ſigned by the <hi>Bps</hi> to their eternal ſ
hame.
Neither will ever this Paper of yours counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poiſe the <hi>P. of
Orange,</hi> His Declaration in reference to <hi>Scotland,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
we are
repreſented as the grievance of the Nation, and the neceſſity of an
Alteration, inſinuated as clearly as could be done without direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
reflecting on our Laws, which though he doth not approve, yet he Judgeth
unſeaſonable as yet to condemn. Nor Finally can all ye ſay for our
vindication, outcry the loud voice of the Rigorous Perſecution, and violent
Oppreſſion, and innumerable Grievances, which may be too juſtly
charged
on our party, and the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are too apt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent and
aggredge ſo, as to extort pity and compaſſion, even from the hardeſt
hearted of our <hi>Grandies</hi> without ſuch an irritating remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
as
you are.</p>
            <p>But to come to your Reaſons, <hi>Presbyterians</hi> will think
them weak e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, though ye had not wronged them by ſuch a vain Title. I
wiſh ye had forborn the firſt which is too <hi>Theologick,</hi> and ſo
not only diſcov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers the Author to be of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> who are little
regarded when plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their own Intereſt, but doth alſo give our
<hi>Adverſaries</hi> too large a Field wherein they are beſt acquainted
and
moſt expert. Ye might have ſatisfied your ſelf only with
<hi>Politick</hi> Arguments, which are the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and ſuitable to
our
cauſe, and would ſeem to be the Sentiments of ſome Judicious Perſ
on of
another Quality agenting it, and ſo be a great deal more acceptable and
conſidered with the leſs prejudice. But I ſee no kind of reaſon in
your
Paper which <hi>Presbyterians</hi> cannot anſwer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any difficulty
and
with great advantage.</p>
            <p>Your firſt Reaſon hath three things in it, which though it be
ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſimply to deny becauſe meerly aſſerted, yet our
Adverſaries will not paſs them ſo bluntly, they give too fair an
occaſion to them, of giving the ſharpeſt and ſoreſt wounds to our
cauſe that it can meet with, and of prepoſſeſſing mens Conſ
ciences
with ſuch evident Convictions in their favour, as will render all your other
Reaſons ineffectual for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading them to favour us.</p>
            <p>The I. thing in it is <hi>(That Epiſcopacy hath the advantage of
Apoſtolick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,)</hi> a very fair Plea and plauſible Pretence,
which ye would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly oblige, the greater and better part of your
Beethren, by making good; But how can we expect this of you, when the
Learned
<hi>Hamond,</hi> who excells all that ever took that Plea in hand for him
not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66087:5"/>all his wreſted Criticiſms of
Scripture, and ſtretched Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations from Antiquity, hath not fully
ſatisfied us in this point; ſo that all the Sober and Learned among us,
except a very few Judge Church Government a point of <hi>Indifferency,</hi>
not
peremptorly determined by Chriſt or His Apoſtles, and that
<hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is preferable only for its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency; And whether
the
Report be true that <hi>Dr. Burnet</hi> hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged its
Inconveniency
for <hi>Scotland,</hi> I know not; But I have heard ſome of the moſt
Judicious of our <hi>Clergy</hi> ingenuouſly confeſs, that though to a
People unbiaſſed with prejudices as in <hi>England</hi> that were to
choſe their <hi>Church Government, Epiſcopacy</hi> is preferable to
<hi>Presbytery,</hi> yet to the People of <hi>Scotland</hi> (who are
poſſeſſed with ſuch invincible prejudices in favours of
<hi>Presbytry</hi> as the <hi>Church Government,</hi> which commenced
with
their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> from <hi>Popery,</hi> and has been eſtabli
ſhed
by ſo many full and free <hi>Church Judicatories;</hi> and Ratified by the
Civil Sanction of three Succeſſive Parliaments, wherein three Kings
Succeſſively were Perſonally preſent, and with no leſs Inſ
uperable
prejudices againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> as a Relict of <hi>Popery</hi>
which
amongſt other corruptions they were Reformed from, and as an Innovation
Introduced, Advanced and. Eſtabliſhed by Arbitrary and Violent Methods,
not
only without but againſt the Conſent of the <hi>Miniſtry;</hi> and
finally as an incouragement of Ignorance, Profanity and Error to the paving the
way for <hi>Popery</hi>) to ſuch a prejudiced and byaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed People
<hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is both inconvenient and intolerable. And
<hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians</hi> do ſo well know, that the ſentiments of many
of
your Brethren, differ from yours in this point, that they will not only
redicule you as Ignorant of the Scriptures, wherein the Names of Biſhop and
Presbyter are uſed indifferently as ſignifying the ſame thing; nothing
given in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to the ordinaty Officers of the Church, is peculiarly
applicable to <hi>Dioceſan Biſhops,</hi> yea, and the Superiority of
one
Paſtour above ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is expreſly prohibited both by Chriſt in the
Goſpel and <hi>Peter</hi> in his <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> but they will alſ
o
inſult over you as impudent, in pretending that for your vindication, which
not only the Generality of the Learned among the Clergy; but all the greateſ
t
of our Champions alſo as <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft, Bilſon, Low, Sutclive, Whitgift,
Hooker, &amp;c.</hi> do deny to be clear or concludent in our Favours;
undervaluing this Topick moſt laboriouſly as being conſcious, it is
againſt them aſſerting, that Apoſtolick Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of <hi>Church
Government,</hi> do not take away the Indifferency and Mutability of it
according to the conveniency of every particular <hi>Church.</hi> And as for
theſe few Learned men, who maintain the <hi>Divine Right</hi> of
<hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> they do ingenuouſly confeſs, that there is no
<hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> in any<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66087:5"/>Church, now which doth
not in
many things Deviate from the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Epiſcopacy</hi> which they
own;
and they will readily acknowledge, that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> as its
conſtitute in <hi>Scotland,</hi> either as to its Elevation to ſuch an
hight of Superiority and Power over <hi>Presbyters,</hi> or its complica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
with ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch groſs
<hi>Eraſtianiſm,</hi> or its Conjunction with civil Dignities, and
Characters is not only qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te
Different from it, but directly oppoſite to it, So that it is the hight of
Impudence to have pleaded no alteration from the Topick of Apoſtolick
Inſtitution, which doth ſo evidently prove the neceſſity of an
Alteration even in the ſenſe that both Parties have of it; and it is
ſcarce ſo excuſeable as the confidence of ſome of our Writers, who
doubt not to ſay roundly, that albeit <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> was not the
Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church in its Infancy, yet it is better ſuted to it in its
preſent Maturity, which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
ugh it
be not a ſufficient ground of preferring humane Inventions before <hi>Divine
Inſtitutions,</hi> yet is leſs intolerable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath ſome
ſhaddows and collour of Reaſon for it; And after the great light, that
theſe <hi>Famous Presbyterians, Blondell</hi> and <hi>Salmaſius,
Parker</hi> and <hi>Didoclavius</hi> have given, to the advantage of
<hi>Presbytry,</hi> in this controverſie, is the only ſhift left us to
evade the Force of their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, both from Scripture and Antiquity
againſt us.</p>
            <p>The next thing ye aſſert is, that [<hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> hath
the Advantage of a Natural Reception by all Chriſtian Churches from CHRIST
to
<hi>Calvin</hi>] <hi>Sir,</hi> Your Phraſe of a Natural Reception is ſ
o
Dark and Ambigous that they will put what ſenſe on't they will, and
perhaps
deride you and it both, by confeſſing that Epiſcopacy had a great
advantage of Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the natural (Corrupt and Carnal) Reaſonings
and
Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Men who are naturally Ignorant, that the Excellency of all the
means of the Churches Edification is their Inſtitution by a Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<hi>Divine Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> becauſe they are
not only
adapted to <hi>Supernatural ends,</hi> but depend intirely for their Efficacy
upon a <hi>Supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Divine Power</hi> and <hi>Bleſſing;</hi>
and who
are naturally no leſs Artogant to add the Invention of their own vain
Wiſdom, as no leſs uſeful and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and to expect <hi>Gods
Bleſſing</hi> thereupon which he hath promiſed only to his own
Inſtitutions. But albeit they put a more Fabourable ſenſe on your
Words
as importing an Early and eaſie Reception, yet they will not only retort,
that ſeveral acknowledged corruptions had as eaſie reception as it, and
far
more early then ſuch an <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> as this of ours, which
(taking
it complexly) we our ſelves cannot deny would have been odious and
intolerable in the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> but they can like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe quite
enervate your Argument, by propoſing to your conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Gradual
and
Inſenſible Progreſs of the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66087:6"/>the Apoſtles obſerved to have begun its motion,
and to
be miſteriouſly working even in their time, and therefore could not be
much
regarded yea ſcarce obſerved in the <hi>primitive Church,</hi> ſo full
of
unexperienced ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and extended Charity, wherein there were many
Paſtours ſo Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for their Wiſdom &amp; Gravity, Holineſs and
Humility, as ſeemed to challenge, and eaſily obtained more then ordinary
Deference and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect from their Brethren, and that from one Degree to
another, untill at laſt through time the Church degenerated into a
<hi>Prelatick Government,</hi> which could not be unacceptable or at leaſ
t
intolerable to the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, being ſo well ſuited to the Superſtitious
(the Predominant) Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of theſe Times, though it paſt not altogether
without a witneſs from ſome of the moſt Learned and Seeing Men then
living, who were not ſo much incerted with the common diſtemper of the
Age
they lived in but that they could both look back to the <hi>Primitive purity
and parity from which Epiſcopacy had declined,</hi> and forward to the
Papal
corruption and Tyranny, to which it inſenſibly and gradually tended as it
ſhould at large by <hi>Blondel</hi> and <hi>Salmaſius</hi> to the
full
conviction of all who read their Labourious Writings. Yea, they will not only
Enervate your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but turn the edge of it upon your ſelf, by
inſtancing the <hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſes</hi> who preſerved the <hi>Presbyterian
Government</hi> from the Apoſtles time to <hi>Luther,</hi> and whoſ
e
Teſtimony againſt <hi>Dioceſan Epiſcopacy</hi> is as ſtrong, as
it is
by our own Confeſſion againſt other <hi>Romiſh</hi> corruptions.
Nay!
they will come nearer home and cite credible Hiſtory, narrating
<hi>Scotland</hi> not to have received <hi>Epiſcopal Government</hi>
for
ſome hundreds of years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it received the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi>
as not only <hi>Bucchannan</hi> our famous Hiſtorian ſheweth, but our
own
great Doctor <hi>Forbes</hi> confeſſeth in his <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicon.</hi>
And
finally they will foil this Argument quite, by ſhewing <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy</hi>
to have met with a more early and eaſie Ejection out of the Church when it
was Reformed from corruptions, as a Native ſtep of its Reformation, then
ever
it had reception by the Church, even when declining from its ancient Purity.
And though <hi>England</hi> hath continued Epiſcopal, yet they will ask
what
reaſon is there for Juſtifying the the Epiſcopal Government, more then
Her Ceremonious Worſhip, and why may not that Church be condemned for
retaining the one as well as the other? and they have too evident grounds for
imputing their Contumation to the ſtiffneſs of Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> as
the
Chief, if not the Sole hindrance of the Ejection of both out of
<hi>England,</hi> as well as the other Reformed Churches; which was earne
ſtly
deſired by the moſt Learned and Pious Divines in the Church, though
when
they found their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours fruitleſs, they chooſed rather to comply
therewith then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66087:6"/>the Peace of the Church and
Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing in this Reaſon is that [Epiſcopacy is by
Experience found to be the beſt adap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed for preſervation of <hi>Order, Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>]
<hi>Preshyterians</hi> will hiſs the Argument out of doors, becauſe its
the
very ſame which <hi>Papiſts</hi> uſe againſt <hi>Proteſtants</hi> for
juſtifying the <hi>Papal power.</hi> And it is more eaſie for them to
reſort our anſwer to Papiſt, on our ſelves, then for us to Evade the
Force of them without either derogat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Epiſcopal power, which we
mantain againſt Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans or Homologating the <hi>Papal power</hi>
which
<hi>Papiſts</hi> maintain againſt <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> We grant
the
<hi>Papal power</hi> to be very much Adapted for Wordly Pomp, Power and
Policy,
but upon that very ſcore deny it to be a Government becoming the Church,
becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Chriſt</hi>
expreſly
diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his Apoſtles, and in them all their <hi>Succeſſors to
exerciſe Dominion as the Lords of the Gentiles do over them.</hi> This
Anſwer to <hi>Papiſts</hi> is an Argument ſo plate againſt our
ſelves, that ingenuouſly I am not fully ſatisfied with our ſubtile
Evaſions of it. And though that of Dr. <hi>Burnets</hi> in his Latter
Dialogues be the beſt I have yet ſeen, that nothing is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited in
theſe words, but the Exerciſe of Civil Power by any Church Officer, over
the Church; and ſo nothing of the <hi>Papal power</hi> is condemned by
it,
but the Uſurpation of a <hi>Temporal Dominion over Princes;</hi> Yet ſ
eeing
this leaves his <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Supremacy,</hi> (under which the
ſubtile <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Comprize all the Power he Exerciſes)
untouched
and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, by the cleareſt Scripture Argument we have againſt
it,
which all Reform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Divines
make
uſe of (even the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> themſelves) in their writings
againſt the <hi>Papal Tyranny</hi> in <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> as
well as
<hi>Civils,</hi> I nothing doubt but the preſent Zeal of that great Man
againſt Popery, would diſclaim this evaſion frankly as the effect of his
former eagerneſs againſt <hi>Presbytery,</hi> hurrying him to a Critici
ſm
ſo favourable to Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And when I have conſidered the extent of the
Paralel place, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. and the particular Application in
Reference to <hi>Spirituals,</hi> which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>
makes, 2.
<hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>laſt;</hi> I cannot look upon that otherwiſe
then an
overſight in the <hi>Doctor,</hi> notwithſtanding of my ſingular Eſ
teem
of Him and his Writings. But the truth is (if we conſider ſeriouſly) the
aptitude of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> for preſerving the Dignity and
promoting
the Intereſt of the Clergy; its ſimilitude to the Civil Government, and
Conformity to the Carnal conceits men have of the Church of God, are (even as
it fares with Popery,) both its greateſt advantage and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage, its
greateſt advantage recommending it to Carnal men, who meaſure all
things by
their Carnal Imaginations and Inclinations, and its greateſt diſadvantage
diſcommending it to Conſcientious men<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66087:7"/>who meaſ
ure all
the concerns of the Church, by the <hi>unerring Rule of the Word of GOD,</hi>
and judge of them by their influence on, and uſefulneſs for the Edification
of their Souls. And alace! the odious effects of <hi>Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> in
<hi>Scotland,</hi> eſpecially ſince it was laſt introduced, are ſo
recent and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, that if any witty <hi>Presbyterian</hi> ſhall be at
the
pains, to rake up this Dunghil, I am afraid ſuch an intolerable ſtink
ſhall be raiſed, as no Aptitude which our Government hath to what is
good,
or can pretend to have, will be either Regarded or Believed by any who are
Judicious, far leſs Sober and Conſcientious. For Senſe and Experience
are
more convincing than all the Reaſons in the World.</p>
            <p>But to be more particular, ye ſay, <hi>[its found by Experince
to be the beſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted for preſervation of Order] Presbyterians</hi> will
anſwer, That what ever be its apparent Aptitude for this, yet it is in
effect, it ſelf an alteration of the <hi>primitive Order</hi> obſerved in
the Church, which did gradually reſolve at laſt into a <hi>total
innovation</hi> of the <hi>Churches Order,</hi> by a <hi>papal
ſupremacy,</hi> which it hath exchanged for a <hi>Caeſario-papatus</hi> in
<hi>Scotland,</hi> leſt the Church ſhould not be ſtill monſtruous
with
two heads, one under another; And it is indeed a hard Queſtion, Why Order
in
the Church, (which we ſay, cannot be without <hi>prius &amp; poſterius,
inferius &amp; ſuperius</hi>) doth not equally require a <hi>Pope,</hi>
or
King under CHRIST over Biſhops, as a Biſhop under CHRIST over
Presbytry; Or
why a parity amongſt Biſhops ſhould not be thought as inconſiſ
tent
with <hi>Order</hi> as a <hi>parity</hi> among all Paſtors. But neither
doth
the <hi>Presbyterian Government</hi> want its Order of <hi>ſuperius
&amp;
infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> for amongſt them ſingle perſons are ſubject to
<hi>Church Judicatories,</hi> and a leſſer Church Judicatory ſtill to a
greater, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In which Order ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is not only that
<hi>ah inferiore ad ſuperius,</hi> but a <hi>minore ad majus,</hi> it is
moſt agreeable to the Church, as it is the Body of CHRIST, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
depending upon CHRIST its Head. And I confeſs ingenuouſly, when they
have
argued that feeding of Souls by diſpenſing the Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments is
the
ſublimeſt piece of a Church Mans imployment; that all power of Church
Officers is only Miniſterial under CHRIST the Head and Lord of his Church;
that though he be the <hi>political</hi> as well as <hi>Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Head of
the
Church,</hi> who as its King and Lawgiver, might be expected would not
leave it
without Directions how it ſhould be governed, yet there is no inſtitution
of a <hi>Dioceſan Epiſcopacy,</hi> that was ever pretented to be ſo
clear
as the Directions given concerning the Office of a Deacon, the loweſt Office
in the Church; But the checks given by him to the firſt appearances of an
inclination to <hi>pre-eminency</hi> among his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> are
clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recorded in Scripture; and finally, that the lodging of all
<hi>Eccleſiaſtick<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66087:7"/>power</hi> of Ordination or
Juriſdiction, in the ſingle perſon of a Biſhop doth not ſute with the
immediate Dependance of the Church, the Body of CHRIST upon CHRIST the
Head of
it; When they have Argued thus, I ſay, and urged each of theſe
Arguments at
length, I have been extreamly puzled to vindicat the <hi>Epiſcopal
Order,</hi> and the ſuperiority of one Paſtor above another; All I could
ſay, was, That Biſhops are as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to overſee Paſtors, as
Paſtors to overſee People, and they eaſily ſtopped my mouth, not
only
by retorting the equal neceſſity of a <hi>pope,</hi> to overſee
Biſhops; But by ſhewing alſo that all Paſtors were ſubject to the
cenſure of <hi>Church Judicatories,</hi> which could not eaſily be guilty
of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance and partiality, towards the ignorant and ſcandalous as
Biſhops; and which by their ſolemnity &amp; impartiality, have as great
and
vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable an Authority as a Biſhop by virtue of his large Benefice, Lordly
Titles, and pompous Train can have: Yea, I have been almoſt perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
to
be a <hi>presbyterian,</hi> when they have reaſoned, that ſeing we
confeſs, the higheſt <hi>Eccleſiaſtick power</hi> on Earth to be in
an
<hi>Oecumenick Council,</hi> and yet allow not of any further power in him
that
preceeds, than like that of a <hi>presbyterian Moderator</hi> in a
Presbytry-ſynod, or National Aſſembly, and not like that of a Biſhop
in
a <hi>Dioceſan Synod,</hi> for fear of a <hi>pope;</hi> Why do we not
alſo
acknowledge Miniſters to be ſubject to inferiour Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of the like
frame, and an inferiour and leſſer Judicatory, to a ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour and
greater ſtill forward, till we arrive at an <hi>Oecumenick Council,</hi> as
the higheſt Judicatorie of all immediately and ſolly ſubject to CHRIST
as
the Body to the Head, without any <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Biſhop over the
ſe
infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour more than a <hi>pope</hi> over his <hi>ſupreme Judicatorie,</hi>
as being the moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual and Homogenious, and therefore alſo the moſ
t
ſutable and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Order of the Church, making the Government of
particular Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Viſible Church,</hi> to
agree together with an excellent Harmony, and moſt orderly Decency. I am
Naturally of ſuch an inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Temper, that I had not the confidence to
reply, that the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the <hi>Oecumenick Cnuncils</hi> were
<hi>Dioceſan Biſhops,</hi> becauſe I not only knew that
<hi>presbyters</hi> have been admi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed Members, and voted as well as Biſhops, and that
<hi>presbyterian</hi> as well as <hi>Epiſcopal Churches</hi> muſt
be
allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their <hi>Delegates</hi> in caſe of an <hi>Oecumenick Council,</hi>
without any other power than that of the Repreſentatives of the Church that
ſends them, Repre: ſenting their Brethren, and not having power over
them
lodged in their ſingle perſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But I perceive the ſtrength of the
Argument did not at all conſiſt in the Quality of the Members of a
<hi>General Council;</hi> whether Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops or Presbyters, but its Frame
and
the Method of its Acting, and<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66087:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Exerting its
Authority:
And finally, I have been greatly aſhamed, and quite confounded, when they
asked, Whether an <hi>Eraſtian head,</hi> an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Body,</hi> and
a <hi>Presbyterian Tail,</hi> would orderly agree together, to make an intire
<hi>Church Government;</hi> and laughing at the monſtruous Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of
our
Government, by ſuch a mix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
ure,
told me that we At<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute an
Eccleſiaſtical Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emacy
to the
King, to unite him to our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, that we may abuſe and pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>itute his Power and Authority, in
proſecuting and promoving it; And that we make uſe of <hi>Parochial
Seſſions</hi> from the Example of <hi>Presbytry,</hi> though <hi>Lay
Elders</hi> be contrary to our prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, for amuſing the Conſciences of
Ignorant People into the more willing ſubjection to us, as nothing differing
from <hi>Presbyterian Miniſters:</hi> But that <hi>Epiſcopal
preeminencies</hi> and <hi>benefices</hi> are the chief Deſign of all, to
ſatisfie the Ambition &amp; Avarice of the leading men amongſt us
&amp; to
be a ſhelter and incouragement, to the ignorance, idleneſs, and profanity
of the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt of us. Thus ye
ſee
how they have treated me in this point, who though I come ſhort in point of
obſtinate Confidence, yet I underſtand the Controverſie betwixt
<hi>Presbyterians</hi> and us, better then many of my Brethren, and have
had
greater advantages ſo to do then the moſt part of them; And I nothing
doubt
but ye will meet with the like uſage from your Adverſaries, to your publick
ſhame, and affronting our cauſe, if ye prevent it not.</p>
            <p>The next thing is, that <hi>[Epiſcopacy is the beſt Adapted
for preſervation of peace] Presbyterians</hi> will acknowledge; that it is a
very calm, gentle, and peaceable Government to ſcandalous Sinners, and in
this has the Advantage of being more acceptable then the <hi>Presbyterian</hi>
to ſuch, not knowing that favour to their Sins is cruelty to their Souls; And
yet I have heard ſome of our own Perſwaſion ſay, that the
<hi>Presbyterian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> amidſt all its ſeverity, was more
favourable then the <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal,</hi> becauſe, though they were
greedy
of Folks repentance, yet they were not greedy of their Purſes. But ye may
aſſure your ſelf, it will be accounted the height of impudence, ſo
much
as to have mentioned peace as the native effect of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi>
and
all the World will be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
aled
unto, whether our <hi>Biſhops</hi> have not been the chief troublers of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> and whether the connivence (to ſay no more) of the
<hi>Epiſcopal Government</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
Popery and profanity, (which are the only peaceable Effects it can pretend to
in <hi>Scotland,</hi>) doth Counterballance its Rigour, and cruelty againſt
<hi>Non-conformity,</hi> (even when accompanied with Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary
Sobriety, Piety
and Loyalty,) or whether it doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly aggredge the ſame, and
render it the more odious to all that compare its favour to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe with its ſeverity to this.
And
ingenuouſly,<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66087:8"/>whatever be in their imputing to
<hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> Tyranny over Mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences as its native
effect,
yet it is ſo ſadly evident that it hath Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremly degenerated thereunto in
this Church and Kingdom, that we cannot doubt, but it will meet with an eaſ
ie
belief from moſt part of the Nation, in ſpite of all your confident
Aſſertions to the contrary, they will grant that <hi>Presbytery</hi> hath
been ſo <hi>unfortunate,</hi> as not only to be rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unacceptable to
our
Kings, being at a diſtance in another Nation, by the cunning
Miſinformations of Self-ſeeking <hi>Courtiers,</hi> the Calumnious
Inſtigations of <hi>Engliſh Biſhops,</hi> ignorant of the Genious of
<hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Pragnatick Influence of <hi>Jeſuits,</hi>
whoſe
greateſt Eye ſore it is. But alſo to be made a Mask to the Politick
Deſign of <hi>Incendiaries</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> (tho they
retained it no longer then their Deſigns behoved to be kept cloſe;) and by
this means to be miſcontrued, as the chief cauſe of War and Blood ſ
hed by
theſe, who underſtand not the Intrigues of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, but after they grant
you all this, nothing, they will confidently accuſe <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi>
that it hath been both ſo cruel and ſhameleſs, as even of choiſe, to
turn, the moſt Serene peace &amp; ſolid Happineſs that ever this
Nation
was bleſſed with, at the Reſtauration of K. <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d.
into
a perpetual Tragedy of Perſecution, Oppreſſion, and of <hi>Arbitrary
Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> manifeſtly of deſign to Introduce and Eſtabliſh it
ſelf without the Conjunction of any other Malign influence imaginable:
Though
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps a <hi>popiſh party</hi> ſtroke in to an After Game, finding
<hi>Epiſcopals</hi> as fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as they could wiſh, to ruine
<hi>presbyterians</hi> (though to the weakning of the <hi>Proteſtant
Intereſt</hi>) hoping that if they ſhould not be ruined by us, yet they
ſhould be ſo weakned and Exaſperaced, as to be eaſily gulled by
their
pretended Moderation to a concurrence with them, for the raz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down the
ſecurities of the Reformed Religion by the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<hi>Papiſts,</hi> (which by a total deſuetude we had rendred
contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible,) to ſhelter themſelves from our Rigorous and ſevere
Laws
againſt them, that ſo at Length <hi>popery</hi> might ſwallow us up
both.
And no Thanks to us that the <hi>papiſts</hi> were diſappointed of
their
Deſign, by the <hi>presbyterians</hi> greater zeal againſt <hi>popery,</hi>
then Reſentment at our greater Severity to them then to Papiſts, which
when
I conſider, I have a ſtrong Apprehenſion that the Lord is about to
reward
their Faithfulneſs to their Principles as Proteſtants, with a Legal
eſtabliſhment of their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in its integrity under a Presbyterian
King, according to their wiſhes. So that you ſee what ever elſe you
aſcribe to Epiſcopacy, your was folly to maintain peace.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place you ſay [That Epiſcopal Government is
found by Experience to be the beſt Adapted, for preſervation of Unity]
And
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66087:9"/>why not, ſay they, the Papal Government for Unity
amongſt Biſhops as well as the Epiſcopal for Uni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y amongſt Presbyters? But they will ſpeak more
home,
and accuſe us of Schiſm in re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ding from the unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed Acts and Conſtitutions of the
Church:
And ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Father the Schiſm
on
Epiſcopacy, intruded into the Church by meer Civil Laws and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently
preſſed upon all by the Sword of Perſecution. Without any due pains or
proper methods uſed for preparing the Nation, for its reception. And albeit
that the preſent diviſions amongſt Presbyterians are much talken of,
yet
judicious Perſons will impute them rather to the want of Presbyterian
Government in the full and free exerciſe of its Authority, then to the
weakneſs of the Government in it ſelf: and I am informed that lately both
Parties are endeavourting an Union; and reſolve to Act Unitly againſt us:
and when the Moderation of the One, and the Zeal of the Other party are
Joined
and Tempered together. They will make a more Formidable Figure both as to
Counſel &amp; Action, then if they had never been divided. And though
likewiſe the former Diviſions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Remonſtrators</hi>
and
<hi>Publick Reſolvers</hi> are not forgotten, and ſerve to highten the
prejudices of ſuch as are not acquaint with the myſterious Intrigues of
theſe times. Yet they who knew how cunningly they were fomented under
Boord,
by the Kings Courtiers on the one hand, and that wylie Fox <hi>Croniwel</hi> on
the other: will not Impute them to the <hi>Presbyterian Government</hi> as
its
native Effects, eſpecially ſeeing that the chief Motive that induced the
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> to rob them of the priviledges of free <hi>General
Aſſemblies</hi> was the fear of their Union, which he knew could eaſ
i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
be affected by it laſt and ſureſt remedie, that amidſt their
<hi>Inteſtin Diviſions,</hi> he might the more eaſily ſetle himſ
elf
in his Uſurped power, without any oppoſition from them, of whoſe
Conſcientious Loyalty he had greateſt Jealouſies and fear. But alace!
what can we ſay for our vindication if they charge us, that while we boaſt
of Unity, we have not kept the Unity of the Faith. For they know well enough
that as ſome of our Clergy are <hi>Socinian,</hi> (the vileſt of
Hereticks,) ſo alſo that the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of the Learned amongſt us are
groſs <hi>Arminians,</hi> who were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as Hereticks by that
Famons
<hi>Synod of Dort:</hi> to which our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous K: <hi>James</hi> the 6th.
Sent
<hi>Repreſentatives</hi> from the Churches in <hi>Britain.</hi> And
thus they
repreſent our pretended Unity under Biſhops, ſo uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned with the
<hi>Purity of Doctrine</hi> to be rather Odious and Deteſtable, then
Harmonious and Commendable; whereas the Commendation of this Church for
its
Unitie under <hi>Presbyterian Government</hi> is ſo great in all the
Reformed
Churches: And was ſo frequently upbraided to the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
Biſhops</hi> by K. <hi>James</hi> the 6th. from the diſpleaſure he
had at
the <hi>Scots</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:66087:9"/>Hereſies and Schiſms
abounding in
<hi>England,</hi> that <hi>Presbyterians</hi> will ſcarce think themſ
elves
oblidged to an Apology for any Diviſions that were<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or Schiſm that
is
among them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I have ſtayed the longer upon your firſt
Reaſon, becauſe it is the <hi>Baſis</hi> of all the Controverſie;
And
as it is unbecoming; the Wiſdom and Piety of the Enſuing Convention, to
be
Acted meerly by <hi>Politick Conſiderations</hi> in ſo weighty a
Concern:
Wherein the <hi>Glory of God, and the Souls and Conſciences of all in the
Nation are ſo deeply Intereſſed.</hi> So that if your Adverſaries by
a
fair and full anſwer not only enervate this Reaſon, but turn the edge of it
upon us, they may ſo prepoſſeſs the Conſciences of the
<hi>Members</hi> in their Favours that all your other Reaſons will avail
little though they were better then they are. But that I may proceed;</p>
            <p>Your Second Reaſon is, [<hi>That the moſt part of the Gentry
and Burgeſſes have taken the</hi> Teſt, <hi>and therefore can never
without Perjury, Vote for the Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Presbyters, or chooſe ſuch
Commiſſioners as are ſuſpected to Favour that way</hi>] <hi>Sir,</hi>
the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> will not fail to tell you that you loſs your
1ſt. <hi>Reaſon</hi> by this 2d. For if the <hi>Teſt</hi> be
<hi>Obligatory</hi> to every point, then alſo to maintain the Kings
Prerogative, whereof this is a chief one, by Law, that he may alter or
diſpoſe of the External Government of the Church according to his
pleaſure, which whoſoever is ſworn to, he can no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for ſhame,
plead for <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> upon ſuch grounds as you propoſe in
your
former Reaſon, unleſs he renounce that Oath in part as not Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,
and
as to ſome parts of it <hi>presbyterians</hi> themſelves, will approve
it
ſo far as concerns the maintaining of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi>
and
the Renounciation of <hi>popery.</hi> And I have heard them Applaud the
Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the laſt <hi>parliament,</hi> in keeping this part of
their Oath: For they know that the chief thing deſigned in the firſt
overture of it, was only the Security of the <hi>proteſtant Religion,</hi>
though there were ſuch Additions made to what was intended for that end,
as
might weaken, break, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare that party in <hi>parliament</hi> that
firſt motioned it, being lookt upon as too Jealous of, and Zealous againſt
<hi>popery,</hi> and as for theſe Additions no wonder they except again
ſt
the Obligation of them, ſeeing that even we our ſelves did expreſs ſ
o
much of our Averſion thereat at firſt: ſo long as we expected by our
General clamours againſt it, to procure an Exemption from the Impoſition
thereof; And as our fear of Looſing our Benefices rather then our
Inclinations determined us, and the fair Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the Explication given by
the Council, (though alace! what ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the Explication of an Oath, that
muſt needs be taken in the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuin Senſe of the Words,) encouraged us
to
ſwear it, ſo doubtleſs the reſt of the Nation ſwore it with great
Reluctancy, rather from a regard<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66087:10"/>of their Places and
Intereſts, then GOD and their Conſciences, (which generally at firſt
accuſed them of Perjury that took it, as being obviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contradictory in
it ſelf, and in many things contradictory to their Light;) until the
Generality and frequency of the Guilt abated, the ſenſe of it, and
therefore cannot be expected, will be very preciſe in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to it, to
whatever confidence many have arrived, for juſtifying it in their
Diſcourſe (to which length as is every part of it, few have come;) yet the
remorſe of their Conſciences for it, is not totally extinguiſhed, at
leaſt is not turned to a ſenſe of its Obligation in every point; and to
be plain with you, there muſt be an Alteration leſs or more: This is both
deſigned and deſired by all Ranks of Perſons: They all agree in this,
tho
they diſagree in the meaſure of it; And next to the ſettling the
<hi>Prince of Orange</hi> in the Throne, it is one of the chief deſigns of
the <hi>Convention,</hi> ſo that your Arguing from the Obligation of the
<hi>Teſt</hi> is altogether vain, eſpecially ſeeing it is ſo
unhappily
framed, that if it bind up from any, it equally binds up from all endeavours of
any Alteration whatſoever any manner of way, of the eſtabliſhed
Government either in Church or State; and when upon this account, its
Obligations will and muſt be trampled upon. It cannot but be very
unacceptable, to plead no Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for fear of Perjury, but truly!
underſtand not how every Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can be accounted Perjury, in reference
to any Article in the <hi>Teſt,</hi> for that part of it which ſtrikes
moſt directly againſt any Alteration, is meerly Aſſertory not
promiſſory, neither does it peremptorly aſſert that there ſhould be
no Alteration, but only that there is no Obligation by the Covenants to
endeavour it, and it can hardly be expected that thoſe who have taken the
<hi>Teſt,</hi> will be determined by any ſenſe of the Obligation of
the
Covenants to endeavour an Alteration, nor is it neceſſary, ſeeing
Scripture, Reaſon and Policy, do all of them together loudly and evidently
call for it in this preſent Juncture, which is a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Cord, more
ſtrongly binding then the <hi>Teſt</hi> can pretend to be, at leaſt in
this point; So that you ſee how little weight is in your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the
<hi>Teſt,</hi> and what it amounts to when duely pondered. I nothing
doubt
but the Gentry and Burgeſſes will laugh at you, for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that for
determining their Conſciences, which all know was mainly impoſed for
debauching their Conſciences.</p>
            <p>Your 3. Reaſon contains ſeveral things in it, huddled together
as if ye would compenſe weight by number, wherein ye ſeem rather to
deſign the inſnaring the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> to declare their
Sentiments
unſeaſonably, about ſome difficult points, then to prove any thing
againſt them; But they are neither ſtated in ſuch difficult
Circumſtances, nor ſo void of<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66087:10"/>prudence, but that
they
can anſwer you both confidently and cautiouſly to their great Advantage,
by
removing the prejudices of many againſt <hi>Presbytry,</hi> becauſe of
the
inconveniencies they apprehend muſt attend it.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing ye alledge is, That <hi>[if presbytry be voted,
then returns upon you the Solemn League and Covenant, as is not only evident
from their Gen: Aſſ: &amp;c.]</hi> Sir, ye ſo manifeſtly betray your
ignorance of the difference betwixt the <hi>National Covenant</hi> and
<hi>Solemn League,</hi> that thoſe who are better acquaint with the
Principles and Hiſtory of <hi>presbytry in Scotland,</hi> will account you
an
Ignorant Scribler againſt things ye underſtand not; As for the <hi>ſ

olemn
League,</hi> I know not what ye underſtand by <hi>[the Natural Exigence
of
it.]</hi> but ſure <hi>presbyterian Government</hi> might have
continued in
<hi>Scotland</hi> a thouſand years without any ſuch League, if
<hi>England</hi> had not given an Occaſion of it: And it is ſo far from
being the only conceivable <hi>[foundation for its parity]</hi> that it is but
a late thing, which was not ſo much as thought upon either at the firſt
planting of <hi>Presbyterian Government</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
the
Reformation, nor for ſeveral years after it was re-eſtabliſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
ſo that it is the <hi>National Covenant</hi> which ye would be at; And as
for
the other, I ſhall ſhew you what <hi>presbyterians</hi> can ſay, for
preventing your Feats, when I come to your laſt Reaſon, to which it
properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lpngs. Its true, the <hi>National Covenant</hi> is almoſt as
Ancient, as the <hi>Legal Eſtabliſhment</hi> of the <hi>Reformed
Religion,</hi> and <hi>presbyterian</hi> Government in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> it
being about an hundred years ſince it was taken by all in the Nation, at the
appointment of King <hi>James</hi> the ſixth: And as it was then
conceived,
cannot be excepted againſt in any point by any ſound
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant;</hi> being an Obligation againſt <hi>poperie,</hi>
and all
its corruptions in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Worſhip and Government, ſo that if ye will
have it even then to be the <hi>foundation of paritie,</hi> ye do
exceedingly
wrong our Cauſe, and do in effect juſtifie the Explication annexed to it,
thereafter ſhewing <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacie</hi> be included in the <hi>popi
ſh
Hierarchie</hi> abjured therein, which <hi>pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> will tell you
was not only approven in <hi>parliament</hi> 39, but alſo ſolemnly
Ratified
by King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, his own hand writing, when he was
perſonally preſent in Parliament 41. And they will ask you, how it comes
to
paſs, that ye who was juſt now ſo fearful of perjury, in reference to the
<hi>Teſt?</hi> Should he be ſo fearful for the remembrance of a poor
Obligation upon the <hi>Church and Nation;</hi> For as to any other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
of
it upon us, <hi>presbyterians</hi> will not impoſe it again without the
appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of King and parliament, and the general conſent of all Ranks
in
the Nation, for they have ſeen the diſadvantage we have been at, in
<hi>preſsing Conformitie to the Epiſcopal Government,</hi> without
pains
taken to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Nation for it; And have learned to be cautious by our
preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitancy.<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66087:11"/>Nor do <hi>[the preſent proceedings
of the
presbyterian preachers]</hi> give any ground to expect the renewing of the
Covenant, albeit they aggredge the guilt of Complyance with <hi>prelacy</hi>
from the obligation of the Covenant, as to theſe who own it as contemning
nothing, but what they are Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently obliged unto by the Word of GOD.
And
this Antecedent obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to every thing in the <hi>National Covenant,</hi>
is ſo common &amp; confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Opinion among all <hi>Presbyterians,</hi>
that they will defy you to ſhew any one of theſe <hi>[manifold impieties
in
that Oath]</hi> which ye ſpeak of in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. And ingenuouſly, except
its
Abjuration of <hi>prelacy,</hi> I know nothing in it, that any
<hi>Epiſcopal</hi> will condemn who hath read it; and as for that point, if
ever it be ordered to be renewed, by appointment of King and Parliament, I
know
none of the moſt conſiderable in the Nation, who (ſeeing ſuch
underſtand both their Duty and Intereſt) will either fear Perjury by taking
of it, or chooſe Miſery by refuſing it. And I hope the refuſing it
ſhall never be judged a ſufficient crime, to provoke the Government to
reduce any ranks of Perſons, far leſs the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in the
Nation to miſery. And I find the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> to be Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
of
ſuch a cautious Temper, and moderate Diſpoſition, eſpecially the
leading Men amongſt them, that I nothing doubt, but they will carefully
avoid
all ſuch practices, as they find do give any ground of prejudices againſt
their Predeceſſors, whom they do not deny to have been over ſwayed
in
ſomethings to an Extreme by the Biaſs, and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of the time they
lived
in.</p>
            <p>Next you alledge, [<hi>That if the Covenant return, no man can
have publick place, either in Church or State, but ſuch as ſhall do Penance
for taking the</hi> Teſt] what <hi>Lax</hi> Reaſoning is this? that if
Presbytery be Voted the <hi>Covenant</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, as if there could not be
a
Voting for <hi>Presbytry</hi> without voting alſo for renewing the
<hi>Covenant,</hi> and if the <hi>Covenant</hi> return; no man can have
publick
Place without Pennance for the <hi>Teſt:</hi> As if there were no other
way
of removing the Scandal of a <hi>General and National Guilt,</hi> but by
par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Satisfaction from every Perſon guilty. I have heard ſome of the
Sober and Learned amongſt them ſay, that the Generality of guilt renders
a
particular Satisfaction, neither Seaſonable nor Practicable-Neceſſary nor
Suitable, and that Cordial Joining in publick Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a Zealous
owning of their Intereſt will remove the Scandal and Satisfie them.</p>
            <p>You ſay further that, <hi>[A great part of the Laity of the
Nation muſt be reduced to ſad Straits, both in reference to Conſcience
and Intereſt]</hi> I know none need to fear that, but theſe who
undergoes
<hi>Epiſcopal Government,</hi> have been habituated to ſuch an
Licentious
prophanity, that the reſtraining<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66087:11"/>them within the
<hi>juſt bounds of ſobriety;</hi> may prove <hi>hard</hi> and
<hi>uneaſie</hi> to their <hi>Lax Conſciences,</hi> which is no great
Inconveniencie, or theſe who have had all their lively hood by their
dependance on the Epiſcopal Government and have been undeſervedly
advanced
to places of Benefit, Truſt or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, whoſe particular Diſadvantage by
their loſing their place, is the publick Advantage of the Nation.</p>
            <p>And finally you inferr, <hi>[That the Regular Clergy will be
turned out, which will reduce the Church to ſuch amazing hardſhips, that
the Goſpel ſhall not he preached in three parts of the Kingdom, there not
being an hundred qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified Presbyterians in Scotland.] Sir,</hi> It ſhould
be your deſire and mine both, that all the Inſufficient, Scandalous and
Erroneous among the Clergy were turned out; and their places were Vacant, till
able Men were provided; rather then filled with ſuch men (who do far more
obſtruct then promove the Edification of the Church) without the hope of
being better ſupplied. And alace! I'm affraid that two parts of three of our
Clergy, may be too juſtly reduced to one or other of theſe three
Claſſes; So that by my beſt Information, the <hi>Presbyterian
partie,</hi> if ye join their Miniſters, Preachers, and young Men, Ready for
the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry together: With ſuch alſo, as have diverted themſelves
to
other Imployments, becauſe of the Diſcouragements of the Times, and
are
willing and ready to ſerve the Church, if there were incouragement for the
Miniſtry, they have moe qualified men amongſt them; then there are
Sufficient, Sober, and Orthodox Men amongſt our Clergy, ſo that they
could
within leſs then a year, furniſh the one half of the Congregations in
<hi>Scotland.</hi> And when from about an hundred and ſome more, they
have in
a year and an halfs ſpace accreaſced and amounted to ſo many,
without the
help of Univerſities; We may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calculate, how ſhort a time will
increaſe them to the compleat Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. But I am hopeful that they will
admit
any Learned, Sober and Orthodox perſon amongſt us upon very eaſie
terms;
our acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Presbyterian Government</hi> to be lawful, our
guilt of
Separation from them and of taking the Teſt; And I know none of us that
will
chooſe rather to be turned out, by refuſing then kept in their places upon
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting ſuch favourable Terms.</p>
            <p>Your 4. Reaſon is, [<hi>That if Presbytery, be not thus
eſtabliſhed in its integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but all that Alteration turn to a
Non-Epiſcopacy, and the preſent Presbyters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in their Offices;
Then
our deplorable Schiſms and Diviſions ſhall continue without a Remedy,
or
elſe the Magiſtrate will take upon him the Government of the Church, and
we
ſhall have downright</hi> Eraſtianiſm.] <hi>Sir,</hi> The
fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Argument is ſo obvious, that I think I may ſpare
my pains<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66087:12"/>in ſhewing it unto you. One would think it
the
voice of a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> proving the neceſſity of an entire
Alteration, rather than of an <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> pleading no Alteration at
all; <hi>Presbyterians</hi> will grant all you ſay, and turn the mouth of
this Cannon directly againſt your ſelf, by Arguing thus, If
<hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> be contained, then our deplotable Schiſms and
Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhall be Remedileſs, alſo we ſhall ſtill have downright
<hi>Eraſtianiſm,</hi> and how can ye evade the force of this Argument
of
your own I ſee not; For it is evident by experience, that we may diſpair of
ever gaining the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> to a compliance with us; ſeeing
that
ſo many years, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Perſecution hath rather alienated them from us,
beyond all hope of either Reconciliation or Accommodation. And it is as
undeniable, that there is not ſo groſs <hi>Eraſtianiſm</hi> in the
World, as is eſtabliſhed by Law, and complicated, and tuiſted with the
<hi>Epiſcopal Government in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Yea they will further baffle
you,
by reaſoning with you thus, If <hi>Presbytery</hi> were eſtabliſhed
in
its Integrity, our deplorable Diviſion would eaſily be healed, and we
ſhould be altogether quite of <hi>Eraſtianiſm,</hi> and ye cannot
ſhelter your ſelf from this more then the <hi>former Argument;</hi> For
it
is more then probable, that few of us would refuſe to comply with
<hi>Presbytery</hi> when once eſtabliſhed by Law; and it is too much
to be
ſuſpected, that the preſent bitterneſs of many of our Clergy again
ſt
<hi>Presbyterians</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, from their Conſciouſneſs to
themſelves of their inſufficiency, profanity, or Heterodoxy, (and perhaps
alſo Cruelty,) which makes them deſpair of Admiſſion into the
Brotherhood of the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> And it is certain that there are
no
Principles contrary to <hi>Eraſtianiſm</hi> more then the
<hi>Presbyterian;</hi> For they allow not any Eccleſiaſtick Power of
Juriſdiction to be lodged in any ſingle Perſon though Eccleſiaſtick,
much leſs Civil; and yet they do neither exeem Church Men from their
Subjection to the Magiſtrates power as his Subjects, nor the Church from
the
Magiſtrates care as her Nurſing Father. Their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in this point are
very Rational, for though they deny Miniſters to be as directly ſubjected
to the Magiſtrate in their Eccleſiaſtick (apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city as Miniſters, as in
their Civil Capacity of Subjects; Yet they aſcribe as much power to him in
reference to the Church, as any Wiſe and Pious Magiſtrate will require;
they grant the Magiſtrate hath a reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power, for reparing a broken
Church, though not a Conſtitutive of conſtituting the frame of its
Government, and building ſuch a Fabrick of a Church as he pleaſes; A
power
Convocative for calling Church Aſſemblies to meet, for the Government of
the Church, though not a power Coercive of hindering them to meet at all; A
power Defenſive<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66087:12"/>of defending the true Religion, and
the
Doctrine, Worſhip, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Diſcipline of the Church, though not
a
power Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, to determine concerning theſe things at his pleaſ
ure;
a power Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſive, to concur by his Civil Sanction with the Determinations
of the Church, and confirm their Obligation on his Subjects, though not a
power
Coactive, to force the Church to follow his Dictates in things
Eccleſiaſtick; And in a word, they grant him all Power even in
Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticks that is Cumulative to the Churches Advantage; though they
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him to have any Privative power to the Churches prejudice. Whereas
<hi>Epiſcopacy in Scotland</hi> has no other Baſis but groſs
<hi>Eraſtianiſm,</hi> ſo that you ſee how much you may be foild
with
your own Weapons; And ye may expect a challenge to expreſs the ingenuity
of
your fears, (of continued Diviſions and Schiſms, and of downright
<hi>Eraſtianiſm,</hi>) by quiting the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> way
wherein ye
Act the <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> in receiding from the ſtanding Laws of
the
Church, in compliance with New Civil Laws, and approve <hi>Eraſtianiſm</hi>
in adhering to the <hi>Teſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your fifth Reaſon is, <hi>[That the Eſtabliſhment of
Presbytery will have almoſt pernicious Influence on the Proteſtants
Religion in this Iſland, if ever Popery ſet up its head, &amp;c.] Sir,</hi>
I confeſs it is more proper for you to ſhew the Inconveniencie that will
follow, if <hi>Presbytry</hi> be eſtabliſhed, then if not. Yet, I
ſuſpect you be as unhappy in this as in the former Argument. The greate
ſt
Advantage that I find in your Reaſons, is that you touch upon ſome
things
concerning which, it is unſeaſonable and dangerous for
<hi>Presbyterians</hi> fully to expreſs themſelves. But alas! you do
here
but touch on that which is the very Sore and Weakeſt Side of
<hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> for you cannot be ignorant of the General
Complaints of,
and prejudices at our Government. As not only a ſhelter and covert to
Papiſts: But as Inſtrumental in advancing Popiſh deſigns, partly by
the
Ignorance, Profanity, and Arminianiſm aboundoning under it. Diſpoſing
and
preparing the Nation for Popery, and partly by its Severity and cruelty towards
diſſenting <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> to the manifeſt weakning of the
<hi>Proteſtant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</hi> And even Envy it ſelf cannot but
acknowledge the <hi>Presbyterian Government,</hi> hath been abundantly
both
ſevere and ſucceſsful againſt <hi>Popery;</hi> and nothing
blunted and
ſlackned in its Zeal and Watchfulneſs againſt <hi>Papiſts</hi>
amits
all its ſeverities againſt <hi>Epiſcopals,</hi> whereas the <hi>Penal
Laws</hi> againſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> were brought to ſuch a Deſ
uetude by
us, that the moſt threatning dangers from Popery could not awaken us to
the
Execution of them, leaſt we ſhould have diverted from perſecuting
<hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians,</hi> by a rigorous Execution of the Laws made in our
Favours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, which did ſo intirely take up the Government, that
not<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66087:13"/>only both Profanity and Popery have been connived
at,
but encouraged in ſo far as they were aſſiſting to us, in oppoſing
and oppreſſing <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians;</hi> ſo that it will never be
believed
that <hi>Presbyterian Government</hi> hath any pernicious Influence upon
the
<hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> but rather that it hath a powerful Influence
for ſecuring it againſt <hi>Popery</hi> far more vigorous and Zealous,
yea,
and effectual and ſucceſsful then ever the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> had, at
leaſt in <hi>Scotland;</hi> And it is evident that the <hi>Presbyterian</hi>
Intereſt, is every way at preſent more directly oppoſite to the
<hi>Popiſh Intereſts</hi> then the <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal</hi> is, which I
am
affraid ſhall yet further appear by the carriage and conduct of our party in
the <hi>Convention,</hi> &amp; that ſo manifeſtly as to highten the
Nations
prejudices againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> more then ever, and make all
ſober
<hi>Proteſtants</hi> conclude, that we muſt of neceſſity have
either
<hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> or <hi>Potery,</hi> and truly I cannot otherwiſe
Judge of
it, then as an Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation, preſaging the ruine of our Intereſt, if the
Biſhops and the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, Gentry and Burgeſſes of our Perſwaſion
ſhall join Iſſue with a Popiſh party againſt the <hi>Prince of
Orange</hi> his Intereſt: which is ſo inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably Interwoven with the
Reformed Intereſt in <hi>Europe,</hi> and eſpecially in <hi>Britain:</hi>
That by adhering to the Intereſt of King <hi>James</hi> the 7th. in
op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to his, they will unavoidably either give provocation to the
<hi>Prince of Orange</hi> to abrogate <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> in
<hi>Scotland;</hi> in order to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and eſtabliſhing the
<hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> or elſe give occaſion or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to King
<hi>James</hi> the 7th. to Redintegrate his Popiſh deſigns with more
violence and ſucceſs than ever before, to the ruine of all profeſt
Proteſtants, and eſpecially of us <hi>Epiſcopals,</hi> becauſe we
have
the Laws up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſide, without any more regard to their Zeal and Activity
for him in his Extreamities, then the King of <hi>France</hi> had for the
<hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who kept the Crown on his Head; or Queen <hi>Mary</hi>
of <hi>England,</hi> to the Counties of <hi>Suffolk</hi> and <hi>Northfolk</hi>
who advanced her to the Crown; or (to come home) then King <hi>Charles</hi> the
2<hi>d.</hi> had to the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who in his greateſt
extreamities brought him home to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſpent their
blood for
him at <hi>Worceſter.</hi> And its certain that our refuſing to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<hi>Englands</hi> Example of Gratitude to the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi>
will
neceſſitate this Church and Kingdom; to ſtand upon a bottom more
different from: Yea, oppoſite unto that of <hi>England,</hi> than if
<hi>presbytry</hi> were Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and will oblige us to ſecure our
ſelves from Popery, by methods as different from the wiſe Conduct of the
<hi>Engliſh:</hi> As the binding of <hi>Samſon</hi> with Cords, was
from
the <hi>ſhaving the Locks of his Head:</hi> or to come nearer, as there
was
betwixt <hi>Englands</hi> and <hi>Scotlands</hi> carriage towards the
<hi>Duke
of York;</hi> and at the beſt will be very hard for <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſ
o
that your fears [<hi>leaſt the eſtabliſhment of presbytry neceſſ
itate
the Churches of</hi> Scotland<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66087:13"/>
               <hi>and England to ſ
tand
upon different Coſtomes which will be hard for</hi> Scotland] are but
feigned
and groundleſs, neither ſavouring of a politick Wit, not an Ingenuous
Spirit: For Church Government is Extrinſick to the Foundation of the
Reformed
Religion, and Proteſtants were at a loſs, if their Arguments againſt
Popery were principally founded upon this Topick, or could not be deduced from
any other: Presbyterians will tell you. That ouly the <hi>Scriptures are the
Foundation of the Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the common bottom on which all
the
Reformed Churches are founded.</hi> But alſo, that the greater part of the
<hi>Epiſcopal Champions</hi> and <hi>Clergy</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> to have no other Warrand, than an <hi>Eccleſia
ſtick
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,</hi> which is a foundation common to all the <hi>popiſh
corruptions;</hi> And whereas ye repeat, That <hi>[presbytrie will divide
Scotland from England, which will open a door to the re-entry of popery;]</hi>
Are they not united in one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Proteſtant intereſt?</hi>
Except in
ſo far as the <hi>Clergy of England</hi> are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally <hi>Arminians,</hi>
excepting ſome few Learned Men, which I confeſs will oblidge them to
juſtifie themſelves by different Arguments, not only from <hi>Scotiſh
presbyterians,</hi> but all the other Reformed Churches, which will be harder
for <hi>England</hi> than <hi>Scotland.</hi> But that <hi>presbytrie</hi> will
open a door to the re-entry of <hi>popery,</hi> will never be believed, ſ
eing
<hi>presbyterians</hi> at firſt ejected it out of <hi>Scotland;</hi> And
all
their time ſecured the Nation from it (more than ever ſince) without the
Aſſiſtance of <hi>England,</hi> which if ever <hi>Scotiſh
presbyterians</hi> ſhall need, they may expect it much more from the P:
<hi>of Orange,</hi> when he ſhal be their King, as well as <hi>Englands.</hi>
Then even when Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> found her ſelf oblidged to give
it,
by the Tye of the common <hi>intereſt of Religion,</hi> without any
Relation
to them as her <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</hi> And as for your <hi>Tautolagick
repetition</hi> again <hi>(that presbytry cannot but alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the Affections
of the Church of England from us, which conſidering our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, will
expoſe us as a prey to the common Enemy)</hi> it is altogether vain and
fooliſh; For the Church of <hi>England</hi> can never be more aleniated
in
their Affections to <hi>presbyterians,</hi> than at this preſent towards
our
<hi>Biſhops,</hi> and as their joyning iſſue with <hi>papiſts</hi>
againſt the <hi>prince of Orange,</hi> hath exceedingly diſcommended
them
to it; ſo the <hi>presbyterians</hi> joyning iſſue with him, by their
Zeal againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> will as much commend them to it. And how
ever,
ye may be-aſſured, that the <hi>intereſt of England</hi> will oblidge
them to aſſiſt <hi>Scotland</hi> in caſe of Danger from
<hi>popery,</hi> more effectually than their difference from <hi>Scotland</hi>
in point of <hi>Church Government,</hi> can alienate them, for ye know the
Maxim;
<q>Tune tua res agitur paries cum proximus ardet.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But many are of Opinion that if <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> be
continued, it will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate ſuch irreconcilable, inteſtine Diviſions
and Animoſities in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:66087:14"/>as will
weaken and
expoſe us a prey to <hi>Popery,</hi> more then any Aſſiſtance
from
<hi>England</hi> can ſtrengthen and ſecure us from it, whereas the
eſtabliſhment of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> would bring us to ſuch an
intire
and firm Union, that <hi>Scotland</hi> could ſecure it ſelf from all
danger
of Popery, without any Aſſiſtance from <hi>England;</hi> Yea, and
put us
in Capacity to Aſſiſt <hi>England</hi> in caſe of danger from Popi
ſh
Attempts; which that Church and Kingdom, by the policy of ſome other laud
may
too readily be brought into, which I wiſh heartily GOD may prevent: So that
ye ſee how far ye are out in this Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Your 6th. Reaſon is ſo weak, that you need no more then ſure
Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation from <hi>England,</hi> and impartial conſideration how the
intereſt of the <hi>Prince and Princeſs of Orange</hi> is ſtated to
abate
your Confidence in it. You ſay, [<hi>That to be for presbytery, in this
Juncture will exceedingly diſoblige
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Princeſs of</hi>
Orange,
<hi>whoſe principles are known to all Europe in this matter</hi>] Sir, ye
are
greatly miſtaken, for I have ſeen a Letter from a perſon who knows her
ſentiments; ſhewing that ſhe is not only willing to give Diſſenters
all ſatisfaction, and if <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> be continued in
<hi>England</hi> to her mind, that the Prince be gratified by the Revival of
<hi>Presbytrie</hi> in <hi>Scotland;</hi> But alſo, that ſhe hath a
particular Reſentment of the ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and cruelties exerciſed towards
the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and has frequently
declared,
that ſeing <hi>Presbytrie commenced with the Reformation of this
Kingdom, has
been ſolemnly ſworn to, and eſtabliſhed by the National Aſſ
emblies
of the Church, and the Sanction of the Civil Laws;</hi> She judgeth it neither
E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitable nor convenient that any other Government ſhould be preſſed
on
that People. And we need not doubt, but as the Calamities of
<hi>Presbyterians</hi> hath begot a compaſſion in her heart towards
them;
So the Biſhops Loyal Addreſs to the King, hath much cooled her Affection
for us, and I wiſh their after Carriage do not heighten her prejudice
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. And how ever, ſhe is certainly a Princeſs of that
Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Zeal for the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> that nothing will
diſpleaſe or diſoblidge her, that is moſt neceſſary and
convenient
for the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Eſtabliſhment of the <hi>Proteſtant Intere
ſt
in Scotland;</hi> for which <hi>Presbyterians</hi> can too eaſily ſhew
the
Re-eſtabliſhment of <hi>Presbytrie</hi> to be the moſt propet and
effectual Method, which one of them hath done already, by ſome Reaſons
which I have ſeen, why in this Juncture <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy</hi> ſhould
be
abrogated and <hi>Presbytrie</hi> Re-eſtabliſhed. Moreover, ſhe is a
Princeſs of ſuch moderate Inclinations, that nothing can more diſ
oblidge
her, then the perſecution of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> by
<hi>Proteſtants;</hi> And ſhe is not ſo ignorant of our Affairs, but
that
ſhe knows that unleſs the <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Clergy</hi> can alwayes
patiently indure a general contempt; or be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66087:14"/>
from
ever having any influence on the Government. <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> and
perſecution in <hi>Scotland</hi> are inſeparable. And for the Prince, I
know not what Ground ye have for your confidence, to ſay, That <hi>[to be
for
Presbytry will diſoblidge him alſo, who has no inclination for the
Realteration of the Government of the Church as he has now aboundantly
declared]</hi> You ſeem to be equally deſtitute of Policy, and good
Intelligence: For as it is known to all the World that he is
<hi>Presbyterian;</hi> ſo his Declaration for <hi>Scotland,</hi> hath
inſinuated his inclinations to favour <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> as clearly as
was convenient for the Time. And though his Wiſdom and Moderation be ſ
uch
in expreſſing himſelf, that nothing can be certainly concluded from any
thing that hath dropt from him, yet it is evident that he will Judge the
<hi>Presbyterian Party</hi> more worthy of his <hi>confidence</hi>
&amp; more
ſuiable objects of his favour, than the <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> for he will
doubtleſs expect, that theſe will be more firm and faithful to his
Intereſt, whoſe reſpect to him is eſtabliſhed by their
<hi>conſcientious zeal</hi> for the <hi>Reformed Religion</hi> again
ſt
<hi>popery,</hi> and who ſhall be chiefly oblidged to him; for reſtoring
their Former Priviledges; then theſe who are Acted Generally by their
Intereſts, and have been ſo deeply engaged in Intereſts oppoſite to
his, and who muſt be in ſome meaſure diſoblidged of neceſſity,
by
Moderating and Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancing their Exorbitant power, and reſcinding the cruel
Laws made in their Favours. And I am afraid that the <hi>Presbyterians</hi>
will be more Active and Zealous in advancing him to the Crown of
<hi>Scotland,</hi> then theſe of our perſwaſion, and thereby oblige
him
to favour them as his beſt and ſureſt Friends; &amp; albeit that the
<hi>prerogatives</hi> which we annex to the Crown be a great Tentation to
one
that deſigns <hi>Arbitrary Government,</hi> yet it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails little, with a
Prince of ſuch a Wiſe and Moderate Temper, who has ſeen his
Predeceſſors either endangered or ruined, by their Attempting and
Exerciſing it, and who knows that Kings Soveraignty, and a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
Liberties, are moſt firmly ſecured, when moſt equally eſtabliſhed
as
(notwithſtanding of the prejudices of ſome againſt <hi>Presbytry,</hi> as
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with Monarchy) I confeſs they have been in the peaceable
times of the <hi>Presbyterian Government,</hi> when King <hi>James</hi> the 6th
and his Son King <hi>Charles</hi> 1<hi>ſt.</hi> were perſonally pre
ſent
in their Parliaments, &amp; had greater advantages for underſtanding their
own, and their Peoples In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, then can be had at a diſtance, and only
by Information from ſubtile ſelf ſeeking Courtiers. So that you ſee
how
far ye are decieved in your expectations from the <hi>Prince</hi> and
<hi>Princeſs</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> who will doubtleſs Endeavour
to
Redreſs the Grievances in Church and State, which ye cannot conceive
poſſible without ſome Alteration, and that greater then ye ſeem to
apprehend.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:66087:15"/>Your ſeventh Reaſon is, a Reference of
ſeveral things to the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all thinking men, as ſufficient
to determine them to an aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion at <hi>Presbytry,</hi> wherein ye go
ſo
far beyond the bounds of Sobriety, and give ſo great ſuſpicion of
Calumny, that <hi>Presbyterians</hi> will repreſent you as a
<hi>Machiavilan,</hi> throwing much dirt upon them only of deſign that
ſome
of it may ſtick, [<hi>let all thinking men reflect</hi> (ſay ye) <hi>upon
the natural temper of presbytry and veiw it in its Tyranical Pragmatick
meddling and Domineer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing effects, which many good men yet living of all
qualities have ſeverely felt</hi>] <hi>Sir,</hi> I know not well what ye
mean
by <hi>[natural temper more then by your natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reception and Exigence]</hi>
but <hi>Presbyterians</hi> will refer their principles to the conſideration
of all Impartial M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, whither
they
be no more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Divine Inſtitution in the Scripture, then
<hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> though they be not ſo agreeable to the Natural
Tempers
of Men; which they grant to be no better in <hi>presbyterians,</hi> then in
others, yea to have been ſo very <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> in ſome of them,
as
to carry them t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> practices.
Diſſonant to their principles, and upon that account more hateful then
worſe practices of Biſhops, becauſe ſuitable, or at leaſt unſ
utable
to their principles; for that which would be accounted Gravity, Dexterity,
Actively and Zeal, in a Biſhop, is accompted Tyrannical, Pragmatical
meddling
and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering in a <hi>Presbyter.</hi> But theſe are not the proper
and
native Effects of <hi>Presbytry,</hi> rather imitations of
<hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> (proceeding from Mens natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Infirmitives, and the
peculiar circumſtances, and torrent of the times they have lived in) contrary
to their principles. So that in effect all that is quarrelled in
<hi>Presbyterians</hi> is the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> practice in ſome of
them
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> profeſſion, which cannot be juſtly
charged
on the whole party; and for leſs on their principles, which have a quite
contrary ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy; And ingenuouſly by <hi>Presbytry</hi> will be judged
by
few to have ſuch a tendency to Tyrranny over the Church, &amp; Pragmatick
meddling with the State, as <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> (as its conſtitute in
<hi>Scotland</hi>) hath; And they will deſire all Judicious men to conſ
ider
whether Idleneſs, Ambition and Avarice in the Clergy; Ignorance, Worldly
mindedneſs and Profanity among People: Be not the effects of
<hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> and indeed ſo manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have theſe
abounded
under <hi>Epiſcopal Government,</hi> that the moſt part will decide
the
queſtion in their Favours againſt us. But I cannot won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der enough, what
could move you to think <hi>[much more deliberately to write of the
Hypocriſie, immortality and Anti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>riſtian genus of the Presbyterian party]</hi> ſeeing theſ
e
things may not only be retorted with great Advantage, but cannot juſtly and
ingenuoſly be charged on the Generality of <hi>presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> you
may
aſſure your ſelf this will tempt them to draw up a <hi>Black Lybel</hi>
againſt the Biſhops and Generality of our Clergy, as alas they have
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66087:15"/>too large <hi>grounds</hi> for, <hi>recent</hi> in
the
<hi>remembrance</hi> of the <hi>Nation;</hi> and they will think it
enough to
tell you calmly and ſoberly, that if perſons unſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs to their
profeſſion be Hypocriſie, if the groſſeſt of ſcandals and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
profanity be immoralitie: And finally, if violent perſecution be the Effect
and Evidence of an <hi>Antichriſtian genius;</hi> All theſe things are
more
applicable to <hi>Epiſcopals</hi> then <hi>presbyterians;</hi> So that
all
theſe Reffections di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected againſt them, will rebound on our ſelves;
And
I am afraid they will ſtick faſter to us then to them; becauſe they not
only agree to the general Sentiments of all Ranks of people, but their
Obſervations and Experience of them is late and recent; Whereas the moſ
t
part of old Malignants, who were formerly carried away with prejudices
againſt <hi>presbytry</hi> under the pretences of Loyalty, have turned
<hi>Fanaticks</hi> ſince, and as perſons convinced of their miſtakes,
both of the <hi>presbyterian</hi> cauſe &amp; Intereſt which they
oppoſed, and the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> which they owned, have thought it
their
duty ſo to do, though to the expoſing themſelves to the Reproaches
and
other Perſecutions of the <hi>Epiſcopal party,</hi> in their greateſt
power. And it is indeed very obſervable, that thoſe who inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
prejudices againſt the <hi>presbyterian Government</hi> are either Young
Men
who never ſaw it in its integrity, and living under a Government con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to
it, have not heard any other account of it, then of the failings and
exorbitancies of ſome of that Profeſſion, which are not the native
product of their Principles, but ſuch exceſſes as the Biaſs of the Age
and Circumſtances they lived in drove them into, or elſe old Turncoats
and
violent Perſecutors, who to juſtifie their change of their Profeſſion
and their Perſecution of theſe who adhere to it, make it their work to fix
an Odium on <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and by their frequent impudence in
repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aching it have at laſt deluded themſelves into an obſtinate belief
of their own invented Calumnies.</p>
            <p>Your laſt Reaſon is, (<hi>That if the Church of England
continue as it is, as undoubtedly it will, and Scotland be reduced to
presbytery, then conſidering the boundleſs and reſtleſs ſpirit of
presbytery, Scotland will impoſe</hi> ſicut ante <hi>an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity
on
England in Doctrine and Diſcipline, which will commence a new Civil War,
the
thoughts of which cannot but breed horror in all reaſonable Men.</hi>]
<hi>Sir,</hi> The only Foundation of theſe your Apprehenſions is the
<hi>Solemn League</hi> tho you mention it not, which altho it be a touchy
point, yet <hi>presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> can abundantly vindicate the ſame, ſ
o as
to prevent the fears of all Judicious Men, whom they will deſire to
conſider that it obliges the members of the <hi>Church of Scotland,</hi>
to
no other thing in reference to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> then what is Antecedently
their duty towards it, and all other Reformed Churches by virtue of the
Sympathy and Communion, that<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66087:16"/>every part of the <hi>Catholick
Viſible Church</hi> ought to have with any other part of it; That its
Obligation is to be meaſured by the general rules of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Truth and
Righteouſneſs; that it is chiefly obligding to oppoſe Popery, and to
endeavour the peace and happineſs of both Nations; and finally that it
obligeth no Man to any thing, but what is proper to him in his ſtation, and
therefore all your fears of a <hi>Civil War</hi> betwixt <hi>England</hi>
and
<hi>Scotland</hi> from this ground, are but Melancholick Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
if
ſo be that the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> ſhall be King of <hi>Britain,</hi>
and ſo long as he and the <hi>Engliſh Parliament</hi> think it
inexpedient
to ſeek, and he and the <hi>Scots Parliament</hi> think it inexpedient to
give aſſiſtance for the alteration of the <hi>Engliſh Church
Government</hi> from <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> to <hi>Presbytry.</hi> But
many fear
upon more ſolid Grounds that the houſe of Commons in <hi>England</hi> clip
your Biſhops wings by degrees, as either to rid the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them at
length
without the aſſiſtance of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or elſe bring them to
ſuch a tollerable Mediocrity, as will render them more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to all the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, then a <hi>Civil War</hi> can be ſuppoſ
ed will
be to any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Presbyterians, who are ſo ballanced betwixt
the
oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe of the Epiſcopal perſwaſion in the one hand,
and
of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent, on the other; that there is no party in <hi>England,</hi>
either more moderate or Cautions when they are.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee how weak a Defence of our cauſe theſe your
Reaſons now appear to be, after they are conſidered, tho with more
calmneſs and tenderneſs then you can expect from a Presbyterian, who
ſe
anſwer to them to your diſgrace and our diſadvantage, I wiſh may be
prevented by this Friendly freedom of mine with you, and I would adviſe you
to wait a little longer till there be ſome better product of the Labours of
your Brethren who are ſtudying this Controverſie, harder then ever in
order
to a learned and elaborate Vindication of Epiſcopacy; and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of
Presbytry, to which if this paper can any way be ſubſervient, I allow you
to communicate it to your Brethren, that they may be the more ſober &amp;
cautious in mannaging the controverſie, but I pray you let it not come to the
ſight of any Presbyterian, leaſt they print it to the publick Affront of
our cauſe, and I diſſwade you as your Friend from the Reſolution
that I
hear you are upon of printing your Reaſons, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever emendations you
make in
them, for it is an old Maxime in <hi>criſt non movendum,</hi> and the
Presbyterians modeſt ſilence, amidſt the preſent Advantages they
have,
will be more commended then any thing we can writ, for our vindication in the
dangerous circumſtances that we are in at preſent. And <hi>Sir,</hi> I
am
hopeful that you will not think your ſelf diſoblidged by this friendly
Duty, from</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your Real Friend and Humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:66087:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
